my name is Maxwell ramstad I'm currently
a postdoctoral fellow at the Jewish
General Hospital in Montreal and I'll be
uh I'll be staying at McGill for a for a
while yeah I'm also affiliated with
McGill University which is the main
University affiliation of the hospital
and I'll be a postdoc in the department
of psychiatry at McGill starting next
September yes so basically my background
is in philosophy and cognitive science
with some additional training in
computational neuroscience yeah so
currently I work on um basically multi
scale active inference so multi-state
multi scale extensions of applications
of the free energy principle to
basically like systems beyond the brain
so like systems well within and beyond
the brain right so what I'm interested
in developing is kind of a multiscale
approach to cognitive systems and that's
that's how I got into the free energy
principle originally so I started off it
more interested in this this field
called neuro phenomenology right so like
the the kind of so phenomenology is a
philosophical discipline originally and
it's about the kind of rigorous
description of first-person experience
so neuro phenomenology was a was a
project it's still ongoing in part the
project to bring together this rigorous
description of first-person lived
experience with you know the
neurosciences and other other sciences
that might tell us something about how
experience comes about like first-person
lived experience yes I was working on
that for a while and I I was looking for
a way to talk about what I think is like
a really central intuition which is that
like all of the different levels of
description of reality are like they
have some
in a way that that's like like there's
there's an equal dignity to all these
different descriptive levels so like you
know we are physical systems right we're
made of atoms so the laws of you know
the regularities that pertain to the
physical world apply to us but we're
also biological creatures we're made of
cells right and and we have a psychology
right and we conglomerate in social
groups that have you know social and
cultural scripts and so we also have
like a rich you know infinitely rama
fiying first-person experience and
somehow all of these things are true at
the same time right so how can we
develop a framework that addresses all
of these levels yeah it would equal
dignity you know with take taking each
seriously and so you know around 2014 I
was looking for a kind of glue that
would allow me to kind of talk
rigorously about all exactly about all
these levels at the same time and I I
met Carl Tristan basically and so the
rest is kind of history it really really
started me off on my current path and
yeah right now I work I work with Carl
very closely and who is Co alfredston
yeah but what's his what's his
significance in this picture yeah right
so Kristen is I think right now the the
most cited living neuroscientist he's
he's known in the field I mean for
several different reasons that what is
is probably most lasting contribution is
well so far has been the development of
basically the statistical packages that
are allow us to perform neuroimaging
analysis and in that in the fMRI
modality so in the 90s he basically
invented statistical parametric mapping
yeah which is the the main tech
used in neuroscience so is that like
taking the data and it's like a
something out of that that enables you
to like interpret the data or actually
make sense of it like one thing but
actually be able to the whole framework
that I'm going to be explaining it's
very complicated
it looks very complicated but
conceptually it's very simple you can
explain it with two circles and a line I
like this thing all right so the two
circles are data right that you have so
observations states that you can observe
or measure and latent or hidden states
that caused your data right so I mean to
just start with the beginning I guess so
you know are you familiar with fMRI
neuro imaging so yeah full mag magnet
yeah
so basically an fMRI machine is a big
magnet and you put people in this big
machine and it measures it measures a if
the signal that it measures is called
the bold signal it's the blood
oxygenation level dependent signal so
this is something to keep in mind
whenever you see neuro studies in
general typically you're not directly
measuring brain activity so these heat
maps of brain activity that you see are
not directly measuring brain activity
you're always measuring a proxy for
brain activity right so in an fMRI that
proxy is is the bold signal this blood
oxygenation level dependent signal so
basically one of the metabolic
byproducts of neural activity has these
interesting magnetic properties that we
can pick up using these big magnets
right so you put someone in a big magnet
you and then you scan their brain using
the magnet and essentially you're
picking up a a byproduct of oxygen
consumption by the brain so then that's
your data and then what you do using
these statistical techniques that Carl
and and colleagues develop is work
backwards from this data to
basically the the most probable set of
hidden causal factors that generated
your data yeah so he's he came up with
this in the 90s and continued extending
these methods so I mean the idea here is
always sort of the same right so with
what you're doing is you're writing down
different alternative causal structures
or models of the causal structure of the
process that generated your data right
so these techniques have been extended
recently and in principle you can model
any kind of data using these kind of
techniques so recently Carl is used like
the newest version of these frameworks
dynamical causal modeling to model the
spread of COBIT as it happens so in this
case like the the the data that you're
using is the raw numbers like so the
total number of cases total number of
deaths and the product the causal
process that you're estimating is stuff
like you know is there confinement what
is the population size like all of these
different parameters in your model that
you're estimating given given your data
so that's that's basically like the the
kind of general framework that he
developed active inference per se gets
into the game when you take the same
kind of framework and say okay what does
it look like when the data that I'm
trying to explain isn't like
neuroimaging data it's the actual
sensory data that I'm generating as an
organism like yeah so that's that's
active inference in a nutshell it's it's
a framework to that extends these
modeling techniques in a way that it's
sort of like what would it look like if
the the organisms themselves leveraged
these strategies to effectively infer
the latent causes of their sensory
states so active inference is something
that organisms do but it's not the
technique used to measure the sensory
data but it's something that that
organisms do like we actively
framework is correct so you can think of
the active inference framework as this
mathematical theoretical apparatus we're
applying to biological systems to
understand them but on the assumption
that the framework is correct
yeah active inference is something that
living systems engaged in basically this
kind of so active inference essentially
has two sides right on the one hand
you're you're trying to infer which
which kind of constellation of causal
factors is currently causing my my
sensory phenomenology right so yeah um
that's on the one hand and on the other
and this is like a crucial point active
inference is about its so this is what
makes it different from like older
Bayesian theories like predictive coding
for example it's a theory of active
sampling of the world so it's not merely
a question of like Basel optimal
perception it's a question of how do I
act such that I bring about my preferred
observations it's just like this this
tie between the entity acting within the
environment taking its sensory input I
try to understand or identifying what's
actually causing what so it's like this
interplay between sensory experience and
action and that's where I essentially
yeah yeah yeah it's a it's a formal
model of the sensory motor loop is
another way to think about it okay cool
cool and serve
the free-energy principle so come first
and what's the relationship between
there's a few ways I want to go about
this conversation because I want to talk
about cognition and information for
assessing and I also want to talk about
I mean the purpose of this podcast is
really to find out what the hell the
free-energy principle is and like what
are its applications and how does it
actually work because in other podcasts
like I came across the idea and I'm just
being like very excited about it and
like a few of the podcasts that I've had
I'm just like oh yeah this thing kind of
applies here I just kind of give a
half-baked description of it which is
one of the reasons why I want to talk to
you just I actually know what the hell
I'm talking about
so do you think would make more sense to
to kind of discuss cognition and
information processing and you know dive
deeper into active inference or just
start with the free energy principle and
go from there what do you think maybe
maybe I can I can show you a few slides
yeah if we can discuss it can we
describe the slides as well just because
it's absolutely just to give you I mean
it's really just to be able to see it at
the same time so that's for those of you
who will be listening the podcast
without any visual support it's really
just the two circles and the line thing
that I was discussing earlier but it's
it's good it's it's often useful to to
see I'm a visual person anyway I don't
know about you know I find it helpful
okay so yeah if anyone wants to check
out the the YouTube video or just photos
so like all the photos and like you're
gonna enable screen sharing long way oh
yeah yep oh yeah right all these privacy
features all right so this is a kind of
cartoon tutorial so this is what I was
saying earlier right two circles on the
line so what you have is you have data
right observable states that you have
access to so again like if you're
working in fMRI for example your data is
your bold signal
and what we're trying to do is basically
go the opposite direction here right so
causality flows from hidden States to
data you can also think of prediction is
going in this way right so like if you
have a model of how some phenomenon it
works you can predict that you'll be
generating this kind of data rather than
that kind of data right that's sort of
the point of being able to use these
predictive models I mean you see this a
lot with the koban modeling right people
have a model of how the process the the
propagation process happens and so that
they kind of can project the kinds of
well data that they will be registering
in the future right so causality or
prediction moves in this direction and
inference moves in that direction so
these hidden states or latent causes
that are generating our data what we do
is we write a model right of the
basically the relations between the
factors such that they generate the the
outcome of interest rate and the
variational free-energy
I think the easiest way to think about
it is that is that it's a it's a measure
or more precisely an approximation of
how much evidence we have for a model
given the data right so like you can
think of I don't know like say two or
three alternative models of how some
data was generated right and the free
energy is basically a model of how
what's Rea a measure of how well each of
the models explains the data like so how
much of the variance for example your
what do you say explains you don't mean
do you mean actually explains why it
happens or predicts what's going to
happen like is it is it it's not an
explanation of how this causes
predictive explanation if we're gonna if
we're gonna like draw from the
philosophical literature and talk about
like models of explanation so if you're
thinking about mechanistic explanation
that there are a few missing elements
here but basically like
which which you're doing is saying well
given the data that I have which of
these models is most probable given yeah
like given the observations that I've
made which of these models is most
probable and the free-energy is is
essentially a metric or a measure of
that that the amount of evidence that
the data makes available for each of the
different models what sorry about your
continuing yeah so I mean this is the
fMRI setup that I was discussing earlier
right so you have a bold signal you have
hidden causes which in this case are the
underlying neurobiological activity and
what you're doing is essentially
constructing alternative models of for
example brain structure or connectivity
right and then scoring how well each of
those models alternative models explains
the data that you're generating with the
assumption that like the the model that
so it's a kind of it's an abductor kind
of or inference to the best explanation
kind of framework for what you're saying
is well you know the the model that most
probably describes the actual causal
process that generated my data is the
one associated with the most evidence
yeah so in in the what so transposing
exactly the same reasoning to the brain
you have this kind of setup active
inference per se where the data that I'm
trying to explain is the the sensory
states of my organism right so like the
states in my retina right the states is
like my my auditory organs like my
cochlea and all that like the that my
the state of mice
you know receptor cells in my skin and
the model here isn't the model of I mean
at some stage it might be but like the
the the model is ultimately a model of
the agent acting in the world since our
actions are the main driver of our
sensory phenomenology yeah so in a
nutshell that's kind of the the
framework and in in all these cases
free energy is basically a measure of
evidence yeah so I've got I had two
questions one I think I'll just put to
you my layman's understanding of it I
want you to tell me if I'm right or
wrong and then after that I want to know
why is it called wise is free energy the
measure like why that term so the way I
sort of see it and I think I've
described it to friends is that
organisms and organisms have a model of
they have an internal model of
themselves and the world in which they
inhabit and they try to enact they try
to act in the world in such a way to
minimize uncertainty or surprise and
this is kind of the the mechanism by
which it happens so this is like the
description of it right I would knew
once that a bit and say that the free
energy principle tells you not just that
you have a model but that you are a
model right so in the sense that like
it's not like you carry around I mean to
a certain extent you do right like there
is something like
a model in the brain right like it's not
it's not quite that I mean what we would
prefer to say I think is that like the
brain embodies parameters of a model but
the whole model is something like the
brains inference activity so look to
think of it this way like this this
issue of model has to do with
predictability right so what does it
mean to say that I'm a model of my
environment well so look we're having
this conversation I'm wearing a sweater
right so you can tell from my wearing a
sweater or you can predict from my
wearing a sweater that it's it must be
20 degrees Celsius roughly in my room
maybe a bit less maybe 15 right because
it's a sweater it's not like a t-shirt
so so there are these like systemic
relationships between the organisms
phenotype right and the state of the
environment these are predictive
relationships essentially so that's the
sense in which you can say that the
organism is a statistical model of its
environment that's that so like the
physiology of the fish tells you
something about the kind of environment
that it lives in so the fish is a
statistical model of an underwater
environment right so and and the fish's
phenotype it becomes extremely unlikely
on land right just like I would be very
surprised to find myself in water all of
a sudden so that's the intuitive notion
there it's not just that and this is
where it departs from older classical
like cognitivist theories to an extent I
mean in my view that kind of indicates
you know classical cognitivist ideas
through through the lens of these new
cool like embodied and active kind of
stories yeah like on the classical story
like I I reconstruct an internal model
in my head and that guides my action so
that that story is still here in part I
mean you know clearly as human organisms
we do construct these explicit internal
models that we manipulate and they're
the same kinds of models but there's
like a broader notion at play here it's
not just that I have a model is that I
am a model and I really okay
okay and you said inactive and embodied
and like I've jumped on Twitter of maybe
last year and I just keep saying you
know in activism and embodied cognition
popping up more and more and I spoke to
Lisa Feldman Barrett a while back she's
great yeah yeah yeah and this kind of
breeding her book how emotions are made
I think it's gonna just blew my mind
complete change my worldview and I guess
very powerful point of view that she's
defending I mean I'm very very very
friendly to the kind of constructed this
a view of emotion that's being pushed by
that group it's very yeah and I guess
just for those who aren't familiar and
Maxwell if I you know don't do it don't
give do it justice please jump in but
what I took away with from it was like
we have all these underlying bodily
sensations that we interpret and then
give meaning to in a way and you know
they could be we may feel ignoring in
the stomach and we may interpret that as
hunger or it could actually be anxiety
and like we directly the emotion from
that and something and this ties in to
what we're talking about here if you're
active inference that emotions in a way
[Music]
the I think yeah emotions are like an
emergent form of prediction and they're
like how we at this at the at this scale
of the scale of this organism how we
predict what's going on the world and
then react to it right and like emotions
arise based on sometimes the mismatch of
our prediction and the the actual
results yeah precisely I mean we have a
preprint that's in revision right now in
neural computation where we make
basically that kind of argument which is
to say that well myself and our
co-authors Caspar Hess who I collaborate
with very closely Brian Smith is also on
the paper these are all like very cool
researchers Kasper is probably the
person I've been collaborating with the
most recently
he's he has a background in
computational astrophysics oh I am still
sharing my screen sorry yeah he so the
paper is called deeply-felt
effect yeah so also on the paper is a
Thomas Parr who is a UH like a it's
basically a genius I mean Thomas is like
one of the most impressive scholars that
I that I know he's Carl's right-hand man
basically yeah so and
Myka Allen is also on the paper and
myself Mike has a cool intro
interoception yeah yeah he does very
cool stuff as well you might want to
check out his his research but yeah so
Casper
Ryan Thomas myself and Carl are on this
paper and what were essentially arguing
is that you can think of basically you
can think of a motion by unpacking it
formally in terms of basically state
state inference about your state
inferences so like higher level
inferences about how well you're doing
with your lower level inference stuff so
we're sort of saying that emotion arises
along with kind of implicit
metacognition but as soon as you start
to monitor yourself and to assess how
well you're doing implicitly you're
you're you're you're moving towards like
emotional types of inference we're like
yeah so I mean to keep it simple in a
nutshell that's what we're arguing in
that day yeah well what's really
exciting about this perspective is that
it brings like you know we used to some
people think of emotions as just like
these useless relics so Adam Ally and
past right there they have absolutely no
function and that if we were rational
they would do away with emotion I guess
from this perspective it's like
it's vitally important to how we
interact with the world and it's like
it's this you could say like is this
compass of sorts that has emerged over
time and it's actually highly attuned to
well out ourselves and our place in the
world and that without these things
without these feelings that we would
just be bereft of any navigational means
we just yeah exactly a hundred percent
and I mean so the the we were talking
about like embodied and inactive so like
all these breakdown there's if you could
break those down in some way typically
which we'll hear about is the four e a
approach right so the four es are
extended embedded embodied and inactive
and the a is effective so we just
covered the a right and so all of these
perspectives are meant to be correctives
or criticisms of the traditional kind of
cognitivist framework susan hardly calls
this the cognitive sandwich right where
you have perception cognition and action
right in that sequence so perception is
basically like taking in passively the
world cognition is creating an internal
model that you used to then that you
manipulate to make sense of the world
and then use the plan action and then
action is seen as sort of the motor
output of this kind of process so the
cognitive sandwich right yeah so the the
fourier approach says this is wrong for
several reasons so that we just
discussed the the a reason that it's
wrong right cognition isn't just like
this kind of flat calculating process
right it's it essentially involves you
know self-monitoring self appraisal you
know the emotional reactions right so
the the these are also correctives of
this cognitive this perspective right so
the I guess the two E's that kind of
come together embedded and extended
which are basically like one more and
one less radical version of the same
claim so to illustrate it I'll give you
an anecdote Richard Feynman
was discussed the famous physicists
right who was involved with the
Manhattan Project one of my idols III I
love the man he's just amazing so
Feynman was talking to this man who had
bought the notes that he'd jot where he
jotted down like a famous equation like
the original kind of notes that where he
worked out his equations and he said
look you know I have a I have a trace of
you know the you're thinking and Feynman
responds no what you have is is my
thinking you know it's not it's not just
like a trace or like a testimony of my
thinking I I used those equations to
think through them on the paper right so
this this comes together under the the
broad rubric of embedded and extended
cognition so the idea that like
cognition is something that is
essentially world involving it's not
just like it's not just like cognition
is something that's in the head and
sometimes in some context that spills
out into the world in interesting ways
it always already involves engagement
with the world and then you know the
differences in metaphysics like if you
want to say that the world literally
becomes part of the cognitive system as
this kind of makes this kind of
cognitive overspill happens like you
know if you if you literally want to say
that when you are writing an equation on
a blackboard the blackboard becomes part
of your mind then you're in the extended
mind cam yeah so the mind is literally
extending yeah yeah you know when it
when when possible metaphysical
inconvenience of this view though is
that it means that like when you're when
you're using Google to perform a query
for for a few seconds or you know
whatever fraction of a second it is like
the the servers are actually part of
your cognitive processing some people
want to avoid that implication and we
just want to jump in is mind synonymous
or like what's the connection between
mind and cognition here because
I mean I think if the cognition as
information processing whereas mind is
very different experience that's that's
the nuance in the literature some people
I mean I think people more safely talk
about extended cognition yeah I think
that giggles just got a part of my brain
and that you know like my mind isn't
Google is a little bit crazy yeah so it
is safer indeed from a metaphysical
point of view to talk about extended
cognition all right rather than the
extended mind I think the thesis is used
interchangeably like the label for the
thesis although you're right like that
is a Andy Clark I think discusses the
new ones he's one of the people who's
who's worked on this a lot his I mean
the original the original paper I think
is from is different Park controllers
yeah it's let me make sure Clark
Chalmers the extended mind yeah exactly
it's Andy Clark and David Chalmers are
the the people who kind of originally
proposed at least the contemporary
version of this
yeah and Andy has this great book
supersizing the mind which which kind of
takes the idea and runs with it yeah but
so I think some people would want to say
yeah it literally is the mind that's
being extended some people want to say
no it's just cognition but you could
also think that this is a bit of a wacky
idea and want to recognize that like
there's there's a situated aspect an
ecological aspect of cognition without
buying the cognitive process he's
actually extend beyond the skull is due
to biological do you mean like we are
embedded within some environment and
that yeah precisely any interest will be
embedded mine yeah extended and embedded
embedded is like the less radical cousin
and extended okay it kind of issues the
whole like metaphysics of those the mind
extend does it make sense to say the
cognitive process you spill out and says
well clearly
get some kind of ecologically valid
behavior in humans cognition needs to be
scaffolded or embedded in the right
kinds of context so it
I mean you know for some people who
don't like the radical the radical I'm
not one of those I won't I want
something more radical personally but
yeah that option does exist though in
the literature mm-hmm so what how do you
think of cognition like what is
cognition and how is it different to
information processing I mean I'm sure
they're very very similar but like when
does a form of information processing
become cognition so there is the right
question I'm not sure I'm not sure
anymore I mean because by talking about
you know like if through this lens and
if I'm writing equations of a blackboard
or like typing into my computer or you
know interacting with a Wolfram Alpha or
something and that's performing its
processing information on my own behalf
when does that become cognition and if
it is cognition then to all my cells
because they all process information my
immune system is processing information
like my hormone is processing
information at all times like my
individual cells if I had to I I I'm
sort of I don't really like these broad
concepts like life Caucasian no but I
mean I I suspect that it's the kind of
thing that breaks down when you look at
like the the kind of border cases yeah
yeah I had a a when I was an undergrad
like a decade ago like I I I had a
philosophy of biology professor who was
an elimination ista bout life
Frederick Bouchard University of
Montreal and that kind of stayed with me
I think he says like what's an
elimination Estelle it's it's an
elimination isten general is someone who
thinks that X or Y concept actually
doesn't serve much of a purpose anymore
and she can be used scientifically so a
typical example of elimination in the
progress of science is like
elemental fire of the ancients right so
you know the in in in ancient Greece or
whatever you know they there were these
ontologies these elemental ontology x'
right where like the the universe is
like for it for Aristotle like a
combination of different elements and
you know that there are similar versions
of these ontologies like across cultures
like you know with different elements
like I think that the Chinese elements
or something like metal wood fire you
know we don't have in the West these as
ontologies didn't have metal but
whatever you know and so fire under
these ontological classifications which
were I mean you know they they were sort
of scientific at the time I mean I don't
know if if it makes sense to project our
modern understanding of scientific
practice back back on 2 degrees but
certainly they were using these concepts
explanatorily right so like you know
Aristotle thought the things that were
of the earth element fell to the ground
right and that's why that's why they
fell to the ground because they had an
affinity to the ground because they were
of the element earth and inversely for
flame right and so so for the ancients
fire was a the element fire was like the
underlying kind of commonality and
explanation for what we would regard
today is very diverse phenomena all
right like so bioluminescence and little
insects like fireflies that was fired
right rapid oxidation of wood material
in like a campfire was also fire but the
Sun also right which we know is in fire
I mean it's it's nuclear plasma right
that was also fire so the progress of
science has shown us that well this
concept that we were using doesn't
actually have any explanatory grip-it
names things that are heterogeneous in
their mechanistic basis and so similarly
one might argue will life is one of
these concepts like it it seems to us at
a kind of everyday macro level that
there's a distinction between life and
life but is there I mean III don't know
and III sort of started to think that
these like working on these concepts per
se is kind of moved and so like III
don't know if I want to give a blanket
definition of something like cognition
yeah because I don't know if there's
such a natural kind to begin with right
I don't know yeah yeah yeah well a lot
of these categories of concepts I like
we the way I think about it is there's
just patterns that we interpret right
and there's and we just give a label to
some patterns and like you know all dogs
have a certain there's there's a certain
pattern that they all have in common but
there's a lot of like just crap there's
a lot of noise it like doesn't actually
correspond to what actually you know
like a chihuahua might seem more like a
rat than a you know a greyhound for
instance but there's still dogs so like
I think of these concepts is just like
approximations that are like good enough
to enable us to work with them right
like you can have you painted me in a
corner right and you put a gun to my
head and said define cognition I would
say something like it's information
processing in the service of maintaining
phenotypic integrity right in the
service of keeping me alive I mean and
so that's another angle into the free
energy principle by the way yeah yeah I
want to come back to it I just thought I
would kind of like go through these yeah
because there's a lot to it right as if
we're just talking about entities or
organisms like maintaining themselves or
like trying to minimize surprise does
the discussion of like how they actually
do that what they are like how I mean if
we're talking about extended cognition
of whatever it was whatever it was like
that's if you're really extended out
there then what is actually being
maintained so I don't know where I was
going with that but um if we were to
bring it back back to the free energy
principle and like in terms of just
minimization of surprise with these
concepts and discuss though for free
yeah sorry I'm sorry that's right you
know it's a lot to take in and it
and like you know for that for better or
for worse like it all feeds into this
yeah so it may be good to put all the so
okay so effective extended and embedded
the two remaining is our I think like
the most exciting personally the
embodied and inactive so the embodied
mind is this idea that cognition isn't
just in the head like cognition doesn't
just isn't just accidentally something
that's implemented in fleshy like
wetware systems like cognition like is
premise on the existence of an embodied
organism and the basically the embodied
mind says something like well a lot of
well you need to appeal to the physical
living body to explain a lot of what
cognition is right so you can at least
take this and I think three different
ways one one would say well the physical
body is Co constitutive of cognition so
I mean you may have seen these really
depressing studies that were conducted
on judges um a few years ago like where
they after lunch or something they just
miss her so much
basically what they do is they plot it
so they it's a survey it's study of
judges and their acquittal behavior so
like basically they they will they plot
your odds of being charged or acquitted
against time of day and so it seems that
at the start of the day you have a
basically eighty percent chance to be
acquitted and as you approach lunchtime
it drops to zero percent and then
there's a bump back up to eighty percent
after lunch so it it seems so that the
way that the researchers interpreted
this is that it has to do with blood
sugar levels like when you have a lot of
blood sugar available you're ready to
consider things like more deeply and
really and then when you're getting
hungry there's just no more glucose to
do the activity so you don't
so if someone wanted to say well you
know what cognition is is just like
rational purely intellectual activity
well I mean you know this is one of the
this is one of the demonstrations if
that isn't the case I mean it seems that
the body essentially participates in the
ignition another example of this kind of
physical embodiment and its relevance is
like phototaxis and crickets is a very
very widely discussed example in the
literature so phototaxis is a behavior
that crickets the Crick is basically
orient themselves towards mates by
exploiting the geometry of their bodies
in picking up sound so basically to
initiate approach of a mate a cricket
uses two neurons just two neurons and it
basically computes which of the neurons
is stimulated first and it moves towards
the that one because it basically its
ears are organized in such a way that
the sound will hit one here before the
other and there so the the actual
information processing that the cricket
accomplishes is to orient itself towards
mates exploits the physical geometry of
its body like rather than having to
engage in a more complex computation the
the actual layout yeah
human walking is very similar I mean if
you pay attention to to this too much
you might hurt yourself but like
basically walking the human gait is
falling forward and catching yourself
with the next leg
so it just it is not the case as as some
people would say optimal control theory
in motor control study it's just not the
case that you have to compute the
explicit movement of every part of your
limb like you're just falling and the
only thing you need to compute is a limb
trajectory such that you can catch
yourself as you fall so examples of this
abound it just doesn't seem
be the case the like you can think of
cognition in a kind of disembodied way
so that's the street just to be explicit
disembodied being like brain-in-a-vat
just all the sensory of what comes in
when I say if any brain appear in the
extreme view but also I mean you know a
lot of the cognitive science like Fodor
style modularity of the mind you know
like all these views that say that it's
the sandwich model that's being
criticized to be right that like you
know you passively intake some stimulus
that you you construct an internal model
and the and so it's it's this internal
model thing the the embodied mind people
are kind of pushing against it's like I
don't need an explicit internal model of
how every one of my joints moves in
space right I just don't I don't need to
compute that my body is such that the
only thing that I need to compute is
where my leg lines to to absorb like to
keep me from falling right but so that
that's one way that you can understand
the embodied mind another way that you
can understand it is to say that oh this
is a more first-person point of view is
that like the the my first person
understanding of the world borrows from
my embodied disposition so think of
metaphors like descent into hell or rise
to glory or something it has to do with
the way that my body you know
experiences itself in its live space all
right so when you're sad you know like
the entire geometry of your body is kind
of like slumpy you know like downwards
we associate downwards to disempowerment
and that has to do with the way that we
experience space as embodied beings from
a first-person point of view so the last
way you might understand it is in terms
of like social embodiment so this is
kind of hegelian it's this idea that
like the
literally the the layout of our worlds
embodies something about our culture so
you know like a I'm sure it's for having
been I know it's the case in Sydney it's
also the case in Montreal like you know
our our streets meet at right angles we
use things like traffic signals and
traffic signalization red lights all
these things that effectively embody
norms so that I mean and this is where
it kind of connects with the extended
mind literature like there's another
sense in which the mind is embodied it's
physically realized in these artifacts
we yeah the the embody not just
knowledge but like you know ways of
engaging the world that like support and
ground our coordinated group practices
yeah and so this this releases the free
energy principle pretty directly I mean
maybe maybe I should hold off too before
just jumping into that you know was
there a final ii am i yes yeah okay good
is that like sort of just too many used
to keep track of its inactive negative
yeah inactive means the cognition is
something that we do so i mean the idea
there is to emphasize like the
sensorimotor loop and to kind of undo
the sandwich model so consider the
following like what is a visual cicada
right yeah yeah yeah so your point is
like our eyes aren't static but they're
constantly moving left like very very
small amounts and that's necessary for
vision yeah it's it's it's the mechanism
of vision really it's like a lot of what
your visual cortex is doing
in interaction with the motor cortex is
kind of deciding where to look next
right so there's a sense in which that
the classical sandwich model tells you
action sorry perception is in the
service of action right and it's it's
it's linear it goes one direction writes
with perception cognition and then
action and what the inactive approach
tells you is well actually action is
also for perception it's really aloof
you know like it seems like specifically
superior as well because like you learn
a lot more from acting than you do from
just perceiving like precisely from from
acting you get all the information maybe
know little you get far more than you
would if you're just perceiving um yeah
I think that's really where the active
inference stuff gets its teeth from yeah
like active inference is ultimately a
theory about how you sample the world so
about how you engage in specific actions
that have an epistemic value hmm and
that help you design big you ate the
world yeah more understandable
accessible and empowering us stacks
within it in a way that's hopefully
beneficial for ourselves and does
results in catastrophe precisely yeah
yeah
and so the I would evolve of them I
think like you you can tie all of these
ease to the free energy stuff I mean we
started with the effective yeah I mean
there's a lot of work you know from
increasingly from our group but mainly
from other groups right now tying this
as free energy stuff explicitly into
mechanisms of effective processing so
just a question on free energy why is it
called free energy because my
understanding of free energy is like
energy that is within a system that can
be used towards some end like yeah so
the heuristic aliy the way you can think
about it is that the variational free
energy is a measure of how much wiggle
room you have on your parameters still
to get a better representational grip on
whatever
trying to represent so there's a direct
analogy in that sense right if the
thermodynamic free energy is the amount
of energy left in the system to perform
work the variational forget energy is
the amount of energy left in the systems
that keep doing like better
representational work I mean it's it's
worth mentioning that like they are the
same quantity in a certain sense like
the the the information theoretic
variational free energy is just a
generalization of the thermodynamic free
energy okay yeah I mean that's where
it's a little bit that's where it gets a
little complicated and that's where like
a background in physics is kind of
useful it has to do with these these
deep relations between probability and
energy so you know this this goes back
to like Boltzmann and stuff like that
like like statistical mechanics so like
if you think of a volume of matter right
like the the more energy is in the
system like the hotter it is like the
the more possible configurations it
could be in right so like if you think
of a gas and gas like you know it's very
hard to predict where any given molecule
the gas will find itself in the volume
it can move a lot if you think of a
crystal very regular relations right
so the the notion that we use in that
kind of context is entropy right so
entropy is a measure of spread
essentially so if you think of a
probability distribution right over a
set of outcomes right so like I don't
know to make it very simple I'm gonna
I'm gonna pull a ball out of the Hat and
the ball can be one of four colors and a
red red green blue purple
like if I if I don't know anything at
all you know about about the balls like
that it's so there are four kinds of
balls and our our bag and I'm picking
some out there are not just four balls
though in the bag there like as many as
I as I need so I want to know something
about like the distribution of balls you
know of ball colors well so if if all of
them are equally probable like if in
reality there's like 25% of each type
right well the distribution is flat
right like because there's 25% of each
type so if you drew a histogram like it
would be a flat distribution a flat
categorical distribution right inversely
if you know there was only one one red
one blue and one green and 97 purple out
of a hundred balls then you would have a
very very peaked distribution right like
it would peak over purple and then it
would be very low over the other colors
so the first kind of distribution is not
informative right like it's you know
it's equally probable everything is flat
we say that the entropy is high in that
kind of context because the probability
distribution over the system is flat
right and so there's a lot of spread
inversely in the second distribution the
entropy is low because the probability
is basically all concentrated over one
outcome so so it's very informative and
so you get this kind of behavior in
physical systems when you consider heat
right so a very hot system is high
entropy the the specific particles that
make up a hot system could be in any
number of configurations
a cold system to the contrary has a
narrower range of states in which it can
be I mean you can see this literally as
water turns into ice right like if the
degrees of freedom of the parts are
drastically diminished as they end up
forming a solvent right so the so there
are these kind of deep relations between
the probability of finding the system in
the given state and the energy in the
state and so the free energy principle
kind of builds on that it I like to say
it kind of jokingly that it answers the
question how can we be so cool
meaning that like as living systems we
were we're in the information theoretic
sense were very cold systems like so the
the the anthropologist Terence Deakin
makes an interesting point he says you
know contrary to the received dogma and
philosophy the whole is much less than
the sum of its parts
consider an engine right for an engine
to work each of the parts that make up
the engine have to be constrained to
behave in very specific ways right like
you wouldn't want to start introducing
degrees of freedom into the piston
movement right because you would you
would get some very serious damage done
to your system so so like organized
systems like engines and humans and
bacteria like live in very restricted
like subspaces of the possible space of
configurations that it could be in like
so you know in in theory you know my
body temperature could be 50 degrees
Celsius or 3 degrees Celsius but for
some reason it maintains itself at 36
and a half degrees Celsius and you could
say the same for a lot of the parameters
that make up my my body and so the
question is well how do you manage to
stay there and that's where the free
energy principle comes in so it's not
like organisms like we're complex
adaptive systems rather like life is
well we are you know remember
we are complex adaptive systems and
because we are ordered in such a way we
have a low entropy
I'm just want to make sure that like
communicating this correctly we have a
low entropy because the probability of
finding this arrangement of atoms in
this state is incredibly low and that
means we have low entropy right and what
we do is in order for us to maintain
this state across time based on the fact
that the second law of thermodynamics
states that entropy is increasing across
time that we need to be taking energy in
processing it in some way to ensure that
we maintain this low entropy state
across time lens so how does the free
energy principle fit into here is it
that's where we're getting right yes the
the free energy principle tells you what
so what keep a lot of people don't get
about the the variational framework is
that it all rests on a bit of math so it
doesn't make sense to say like you know
the is is is the free energy principle
true or false it's like well it's the
same status as calculus it's look like
you know you don't you don't like
disprove calculus like if there's a
problem with calculus you derive a
contradiction right or are you sure that
this or that kind of bit of the
formalism doesn't follow and the free
energy principle is very much the same
thing it like if we're really just
drilling down and like just looking at
it from the most technical point of view
what it's basically telling you is what
must necessarily be true of any system
that exists if non-equilibrium
steady-state so let me unpack that
equilibrium is where is the end point
right so the second law of
thermodynamics is about equilibrium
essentially it's telling you like we're
systems were cut we're almost all
physical systems are kind of converging
towards those where like we just think
it's a fun plate right like once out a
hot plate it's hot there that's cold
over time the home plate will be the
same temperature it all it's not just
the nature of boors a vacuum is that
nature abhors a gradient right like
nature
things to be perfectly flat so again
it's the entropy thing it's like if
nature is trying to flatten all the
probability distributions right so I I'm
a big fan of ginger ale I like a nice
cold fizzy ginger ale but much to my
chagrin if I leave it on the counter for
30 minutes it'll become room temperature
and not fizzy right so this kind of room
temperature not fizzy is equilibrium
right it's just like the the and you
know if you pushed it to the extreme and
you I left
the thing I left the the you know the
glass of ginger ale on the counter for
two billion years well it will have
completely dissolved and sublimated into
the into the environment I mean like
after two billion years like potentially
like even the solid material of the
glass would have started to like diffuse
into the environment like through
sublimation there might not even be a
glass there left anymore so one thing to
notice about systems in nature is that
self-organization itself is almost
always in the service of increasing
entropy and returning to equilibrium so
that that fact is underappreciated I
think in in the study of self organized
complex adaptive systems like so think
of a lightning bolt
alright so lightning bolt arises because
you have a charge gradient right so like
you know it because of like the movement
of particles and whatnot like you get
more electrons stuck in one place than
in another and the in striking the
lightning bolt corrects the balance
right sorry corrects the the imbalance
and it brings the system closer to
equilibrium so the same is true of a
tornado right so you have a temperature
gradient in the tornado yeah typically
have very cold and very hot air that
kind of meet in a way that they're
stacked and then like the tornado
it looks like it's increasing order
locally and it does locally but
but the cost of it is the increased
disorder globally and the same is true
of the lightning bolt the lightning bolt
self-organizes around a charge gradient
and in striking it consumes the gradient
around which it was self-organized yes
so this is true of almost every
self-organizing system they increased
entropy and they consumed energy to stay
to sell self-organized so if you think
of the star for example you say increase
the entropy do you mean locally or do
you mean global good yeah yeah because
that's the important distinction right I
was outside and confused because I'd
like to know well stuff organized
systems want to say self-organizing they
process or using they use energy to put
it crudely think of how much think think
of how much matter you have turned into
poop over the last year yeah I mean just
just dirt like think of how much
literally the raw amount of matter that
you have disorganized in order to
maintain your own integrity this is this
is the rule I mean yeah is the rule
right it's like yeah exactly a lot of
energy right like it I mean all of the
energy on planet earth basically used by
living organisms except them like these
weird sub marine ecosystems come from
the Sun but I think the the figure is
something like it takes 10 times more
energy to create a star than a star will
output in its whole life in terms of
like the the actual energy that it takes
to create a star right like everything
kind of yeah so even a star is is a is a
machine that primarily serves to
increase the entropy of the universe so
having said all this you know living
systems like bunny rabbits and tigers
and and you know you and I don't self
organize to equilibrium
we self-organized to this other thing
that's known as a non-equilibrium
steady-state so the difference is kind
of intuitive let's take a simple example
my body temperature is 36 and 1/2
degrees my core body temperature that is
and so that's a steady-state like my
body set that as like a point and my
homeostasis makes sure that I maintain
myself at that point so I mean this is a
contrary - like I was saying basically
all other kinds of self work in my
systems the don't self-organized to this
steady state but rather self-organized
to equilibrium for for organisms
equilibrium is death right if I became
if I if my core body temperature kind of
diffused to room temperature I would die
like quite literally so the free energy
principle basically tells you what must
be true of an organism if it exists at
non equilibrium steady state and so it's
it's literally starting from information
theory and dynamical systems theory and
then like formulating ok so like what
does the system look like when it exists
at non equilibrium steady state in these
regimes and what must be true of it for
it to continue existing in this in the
state in a nutshell that's what the free
energy principle does so how do we begin
to there's a few there's a few ways I
want to go over here one is just
describing or explaining how we'll be
sort of measuring these things or like
is this found in all I guess this is
when you mentioned it's kind of like a
tool like calculus it's it's not a thing
that's observed it's a way of observing
or way of describing these things right
and this is just something that was a
characteristic of life so
this is where it gets a little subtle
it's so that having said everything
about the non-equilibrium steady-state
okay so I didn't tell you what the free
energy principle does I just kind of set
up the problem that it answers right so
to recap organisms existed
non-equilibrium steady-state right so
now we know what that means right so
they don't they don't self-organized to
equilibrium which would just you know
it's it's my flat and room temperature
you know Jenny right all right III
self-organized to my phenotype I
self-organized to the set of states that
I occupy most of the time right that
make me the kind of creature that I am
right so if I'm a fish I self-organized
to a set of states that allow me to
exist as a fish right so I'll grow gills
right and fins and so on and you know
analogous things can be said for you
know self-organization as a human so
given that I exist a non equilibrium
steady-state the free energy principle
tells me what must be true of me you
know provided that I continue existing
at non equilibrium steady state so in a
nutshell that the free energy principle
says is that if I exist at non
equilibrium steady state it will look as
if my behavior is being generated by a
statistical model of my environment so
that's the crucial point is that it's
are you familiar with Dennett's
Daniel Dennett's like the intentional
stance no okay so it's a position in
philosophy the basically says well what
why why is it that we we are able to
treat each other as intentional systems
ayiiia systems that have aboutness right
that are able to respond adaptively and
intelligently to the environment so then
it says well essentially it's that we we
we adopt the
intentional stance it's not that there's
something like intentionality in systems
it's that we we for certain purposes
adopt towards others a certain
perspective that describes to them
beliefs and desires and so on and for
our survival and and insofar as our
capacity to explain the behaviors of
others is involved its adaptive and
efficient to do so right so this is the
so called intentional stance so the free
energy principle has a similar flavor it
says like it looks as if organisms the
behavior of organisms is being generated
by a statistical model that the organism
is so yeah and the statistical model
like I just I really like the idea of
like I think the most intuitive way for
me to think about it is the minimization
of surprise which you could think of as
this if we are a statistical model as in
that we are like as you said it's not
just our brains but our entire being is
the model then I like this notion of
minimizing seeing that as a way of
minimizing surprised because surprise is
not always good right especially for
life surprise could be a lion or it
could be a disease it could be anything
it could be I mean in terms of if you're
looking at it like just very technically
the way that it's set up is that like
surprising the states are not good for
the most part and we're talking about
internal states but no oh yeah yeah okay
so I mean it gets a little subtle
because humans are also averse to
boredom for example right so yeah it's
just about making sure that you never
are surprised right it's just that there
there are certain kinds of observations
about which you don't want to be
surprised
yeah right so like
I currently observed that there's a lot
of breathable air around me right I'm
breathing very freely right now
similarly like my observations are
consistent with my belief that my core
body temperature is thirty six and a
half degrees that I still have four
limbs right like that so that there are
there are some beliefs about the typical
things that I should be observing that
like you know challenging those beliefs
is very bad for my survival right like
so if suddenly the first belief that I
mentioned right there's a lot of
breathable air was suddenly like put
into question by by sensing evidence
counter to it I would probably act in a
way to make sure that yeah different was
gonna happen because I I need air so
that there's a sense in which like the
free energy principle builds in like a
good part of the the normativity
involved in existing as a as a prior
preference over certain kinds of data or
like observable outcomes like that I fir
- generate certain kinds of data that
doesn't mean though that like I I want
to eliminate surprise entirely know what
that makes a lot of I mean because you
for one you can't and two surprises
informative right and as you go up scale
so this is where I'm very excited about
what the reason I wanted to speak in I
think it applies to some of the work
that you've done you know about how this
is found across scales and yes that
every time but given that we are
embedded in our own actions change the
environment that as we increase as the
scale increases there is always more to
know and we can always be surprised and
now then we're at this as planned now we
are a planetary species we have a whole
host of things to be surprised by now
that we there's a sense in which like
the so this notion of prediction error
it effectively replaces the the
classical notion of signal so consider
the following like a one-to-one map like
a 1:1 scale
Knapp would be completely useless right
like I mean imagine like you know you're
visiting New York for the first time
like a one-to-one scale map like you
know it would be it would be like bigger
than a building right like the actual
amount of paper so like in order to be
useful at all a model has to be simpler
than the the data space that it's
modeling right you know like so there's
a sense in which like just by
construction for a model to be useful it
will have to generate error and so in
the kind of this is slightly broader
than active inference and the free
energy principle it's the Bayesian brain
with slightly older you know approaches
developed like in the 90s and 2000's so
like from that point of view signal like
the signal that the organism perceives
is a prediction error like because
basically the idea is like if if the if
my sensory observations match my
expectations there's no sense in
processing it it's just it's what I
expected whatever there's no sense in a
noble izing my metabolic resources to
address a percept that I had perfectly
predicted and that you know if I'm
hooked up in the right way like you know
addicted perception just kind of roll
off you know yeah yeah I'm needing to
engage them yeah so that there's a sense
in which like all signal is error
it's efficient that way because yeah
yeah yeah yeah and that's that's what
I'm Lisa Feldman Barrett was that's what
she I don't think she discovered but
that's what she spoke about a lot I kind
of forgot about that part of it that's
um that's really interesting it
underlies a lot of the like motivation
for the approach right so we're saying
like an organism embodies a statistical
model of its environment meaning that
like there's a kind of average value
that it expects to encounter for
different classes of stimuli right and
the organism will only be prompted to
process like a stimulus when there's a
deviation from what it expected yeah and
so there's an extra twist that makes it
especially interesting and that makes it
robust to some objections it's not as a
darkroom problem I think it's an on
problem honestly but so the Darkman
problem says okay well if there's this
surprise minimization thing going on why
isn't it the case that I just find a
dark room and stay there because that
would be a great way to avoid all
prediction error right if I predict that
I'm in a dark room and I'm in a dark
room there's no prediction error and so
why don't I just do that two reasons I
think kind of spring to mind immediately
the first is that you can have an X I
mean
so we're embodied right to bring it back
to the embodied mind like my body is a
statistical model like it's a I embody
expectations about you know my
environment so for example I have
expectations about my blood sugar level
right and so staying in a dark room with
no food is gonna you know frustrate some
of my expectations about my blood sugar
level such that at some point I'm gonna
you know move out there are more direct
ways to gerrymander it a bit and I can
see why you might find those like less
principal you could for example just
stipulate that you have an aversion to
you know encountering no surprise for a
while there's no reason why you couldn't
do that like just to bake it into I mean
but there's a more principled way to do
the same
so this free energy quantity that we've
been talking about what you can do is
kind of think about how it evolves in
the future so you can think like for
every possible course of action that I
can take how much free energy is
associated with that with that course of
action so when you have this future a
future-oriented or this kind of this
extended construction of the free energy
it's called the expected free energy it
turns out that for some using these nice
mathematical tricks you can decompose
that into basically a pragmatic
component which is basically how close
do I get to my preferred observations
and an epistemic component which is
irrespective of how close I get to my
preferred observations am i gaining any
information by making this observation
so like I don't know it's it's 3:00 in
the morning you come back from the pub
you're hungry right you stumble into the
kitchen right but it's 3:00 in the
morning so it's dark the first thing you
do is open the light well I mean from a
kind of classical kind of expected
utility theory perspective that's a bit
puzzling because you don't get any
immediate gratification from opening the
light you know it's not like it's not
like you're getting like you know like
sexual gratification or like you know
food stuff immediately from opening the
light the old but we do though right
like you know we open the light and the
reason we do is that like there's
information gained from doing that so so
an action basically has an pragmatics
component the the pragmatic affordance
or a value of a of a policy and the
epistemic component and the value or
policy so you another way to respond to
this dark room objection is to say well
look like the organism also acts to
basically increase its epistemic grip on
its world so there's a point at which
like the
there's nothing more to gain from just
like staying in the darkroom and so
you'll probably you know here's
something outside the room and want to
disambiguate what that is you know yeah
I'm curious about what the implications
are or what we know about this and
social species where species have to
coexist and collaborate
you know they can't exist in isolation
they need these organisms need to
interact and cooperate in order to exist
and I'm thinking of you know bees and
ants but also you know humans um what
does I worked a lot on this like that's
sort of one of my the main thrust of my
research is extending this active
inference business to a social and
cultural behavior and I guess the main
idea there is that these these models
that I was talking about earlier these
statistical models so they're called
generative models because so technically
these models there they are the joint
probability distribution over systemic
States and external States so systemic
being the organism yeah exactly
it's internal States it's active States
its sensory states and some some set of
external states yeah yeah
so wait sorry I lost my I lost my idea
there yeah I think I've been there once
or twice this conversation - we're
talking about social species I'm sorry
yes so they're the so these bottles I
was just saying this because they're
called generative because because of the
setup that I was describing earlier
right you can use these models to
generate the kind of data that you would
expect if the model was the case right
so like having a generative model kind
of sets you up with I don't want it like
I don't necessarily want to say
normative but
the kind of it sets you up with like the
a a grip on the kind of typical
observations that you would make given
the kind of creature that you are right
so that's that's literally what what it
does it's a it's the joint probability
distribution over some external states
right and some organismic states so the
way that we do cultural and social
dynamics under this approach is to say
okay what happens if several agents
share the same model so again like the
model essentially harnesses your
expectations about the way states of the
world which could be social states
hookup to the kind of typical
observations that you make right so one
way to talk about sharing the social
world is in terms of sharing a
generative model ie sharing a kind of
statistical model about how the
observations that I make typically a
pond two states of the world and if if
we were to just translate into everyday
language like people seeing the same
phenomena in a set in the same way
exactly sharing the same expectations
yeah and prior beliefs about the world
and about how my sensory phenomenology
relates to aspects of the world yeah
nutshell so I mean there's some pretty
compelling simulation work done on it's
by Chris frith and Carl Fuerst and
mainly although it's been extended on
basically little agents
it's like birdsong simulations so you
have a little agents that sing a song
and they're able to coronate like little
simulated birds they're essentially able
to coordinate their singing behavior and
recognize when they're singing versus
when the other bird is singing by
sharing the same generative model yeah
so I mean the idea is sort of that if we
share the same expectations about the
way that states of the world map on to
our observations and the way that
states of the world involved then you
know there's a sense in which each of
our coordinated each of our individual
behaviors end up coordinated because we
expect the same outcomes right yeah so
so that's how we and Dewey so it's like
I think about it like this if we're all
I don't know drivers are something wrong
people and we all have a map if the map
is the same and we're kind of working
with other people who kind of go on the
same roads or in some if we're all
following the same map we'll end up
going to the same places if there's like
some sort of directionality or you know
X is the spot I know that I've got a
compass is the map I will go in that
direction at everyone else will but it's
exactly not the same and people might
come that's the and yeah so there's some
cool results
this is Eddie bulik who's currently at
UCL she's done she's done a lot of hyper
scanning are you familiar with this
hyper scanning or socials guess it's a
multi brain neuroimaging it's like the
new thing right now so like rather than
just scan one brain yeah like in
real-time you hook up several people to
the fMRI or EEG or whatever your
modality is and you you can you can
measure brain to brain information
transfer yeah it's it's a cool it's a
cool do a lot of what we're doing now is
gonna be combining like this hyper
scanning set up with active inference
malls that use multiple agents so that
we can I mean are the participants doing
things like like I first think of like
video games sports choir jazz bands it
depends I mean like there's been hyper
scanning done on people the cool thing
about some of this hyper scanning stuff
using more portable technologies that
you can have ecologically realistic
settings so that they've used EEG which
are these like caps that pick up scalp
electrical activity in operas for
example to get like people's real-time
impressions of like seeing
a show together in this case it's it has
more to do I mean these are techniques
they're used in several different
studies I mentioned Etta's work because
she has some cool data where like it
seems that wrote I mean this is one of
the things that I have to check with her
if we can put it on the internet yet so
we might have to cut this out but this
may just be for your own benefit but
like she has this cool work that shows
that basically romantic partners don't
don't
they don't attuned to each other anymore
they don't have to like that they're not
actively trying to adjust to the other
person anymore
because they have they have such an
accurate model of the other person so
there's like a sweet spot there's like
those predictions if your models are not
similar enough like if you don't speak
the language and you're not from the
same culture there's not enough
commonality to start adjusting but if
you're if you're too similar there's no
need to adjust yeah yeah yeah so there's
like an inverse you curve kind of thing
going we're like on the one end like
there's perfect synchrony because you
have the same model
so this it's like these romantic couples
that don't really need to check with
each other anymore because they just
know they know what their partner thinks
right it's like oh people they just
don't talk to each other because they're
just telecommunication exactly yeah yeah
so so like the the kind of overall
framework you know kind of gives you
this inverted you where like you know
the yeah it's all about the extent to
which you share a generative model and
so yeah I think that that kind of well
illustrates like this the kind of
generalizability of the approach yeah
yeah I be we I mean this is a bit sad I
guess but be funny to see if it
predicted divorce you know like
incoherent models just like I'm sure
that I'm sure they would right because
that's how a lot of divorces arise right
people acting in one way that doesn't
you know here with what their partner
wants and over time yeah I mean so the
these these techniques I think are being
scaled up
more like you know interesting you know
socially rich human behaviors yeah and
yeah so it has to do with the full
pipeline I mean so I've been I've been
talking about like the the side of this
that I'm like coming from Moore which is
like the the kind of computational
modeling side but I mean to to return to
the if you don't mind me sharing my
screen for a second again place place
I'll of course describe what's going on
[Music]
yeah this is what I wanted so the the
whole the full pipeline that we're
considering is this kind of thing where
like what I've been talking long mainly
so what we're seeing now for those of
you listening is three circles so you
have two circles on the side that are
pointing towards a middle circle the
middle circle is data and the two side
circles are the modeling bit that I've
been talking about a lot in the
experimental side of things that I I
alluded to a bit when we were discussing
this fMRI stuff right so like and this
relates to our earlier discussion of
like you know is this an explanation
really like the full stent the full
pipeline is this thing here it's it's a
combination of experimental and modeling
techniques that are kind of joined at
the data so basically you you start with
either end so suppose you start with an
experimental setup like we were just
discussing your your which you have is
like people performing a psychological
task and you're getting either you know
neurological or behavioral data are both
from them right so that's this side of
the equation here right so you have an
experimental setup that generates some
data and then what you can do is write
down a generative model of the kind that
I just described
or rather what you what you end up doing
is writing families of generative model
the kind that I just described that each
represent a hypothesis about the causal
structure of what generated this process
that actually generated my data so like
it so in this in this instance like each
of these models is is a model of one
possible hypothesis about you know the
the causal factors involved in the
experimental setup the generated the
data in the first place right so you
construct these models you score them
using the variational free-energy to
find the most probable one right and so
that that model that you end up
selecting encodes a hypothesis about the
structure of the process involved in the
experimental setup so now what you can
do is kind of bootstrap your thing right
like you can use the fitted model right
to make better predictions about what
kind of things you would have to test
experimentally so then you can refine
your experimental setup and generate
better data and then using this better
data you can construct new models that
are more refined to make pointed
hypotheses about the structure of the
process that you're investigating and so
you get this cool kind of bootstrapping
self REITs like virtual racing feedback
ions yeah that's really that's an
underappreciated point like you know III
I see these kind of partial criticisms
of the active inference framework that
go will you know like surely these
computational models aren't a full story
you know like you're you're not really
talking about the mechanistic
implementation which is fair it's but
the thing to keep in mind is that the
full framework necessarily includes this
neuroimaging aspect that makes very
pointed hypotheses about brain structure
for example yeah and in fact if you
think about it the origins of the
approach you know are in fMRI so like
the the behavioral modeling thing that's
kind of become front and center that's
gained so much attention
is just one part of this whole process I
mean so as a philosopher the thing that
gets me really excited recently is this
thing computational nosology so this is
where we're moving towards a kind of
meta science or a meta Bayesian meta
science so I mean to rehearse the
argument you can have if you apply this
framework to some set of experimental
data like a bolt signal then what you're
doing effectively is writing a model of
the underlying neurobiological activity
that might have caused your data right
we've discussed this active inference is
takes the same kind of approach and says
okay here the data are the sensory
signals that I generate in engaging with
the environment and the model is a model
of me acting in the world okay so what
what happens when the data that we want
to explain is the result of the
scientific activity itself so for
example what happens if the data that I
want to explain is a psychiatric
diagnosis right what I want to explain
is the diagnosis of you know the actual
diagnostic act of you know saying
telling a patient you have schizophrenia
well then the model is becomes a model
of the diagnostic process and then lo
and behold we are part of that model as
clinicians and experimenters right like
the the generative models that we use in
this sense of the active inference sense
right the the models that I bring to
bear as a clinician to make sense of the
clinical phenomenon and presented right
and also these models like the models of
how like the the hemodynamics and so on
like real fever
exactly all of that is oh in this kind
of meta Bayesian approach where like the
the full model of the diagnostic process
includes the models that I use this as a
theoretician and the the clinical models
that are used by like a psychiatrist so
this is where we're going like so it
seems to me it's just like the scope of
what is actually important is far
broader it
not just the actual experiments of the
models themselves but it's those who are
actually well running them and actually
coming up with it yeah so wet is where's
the boundary what is it I mean so
remember the the free energy principle
is a theory of a non equilibrium steady
state so if if a system exists at non
equilibrium steady state it can be
explained by the free energy principle
this isn't just a hypothesis by virtue
of what it means to exist at non
equilibrium steady state for principled
reasons you can appeal to the active
inference framework a very cool stuff to
do it so the extent that science is just
another you know large-scale human
activity with its own not equal to Rijo
steady states then it can also be model
yeah well this kind of brings me to the
point about social systems and and all
that and I guess taking this and
applying it to our politics and our
societies and I mean we all have is
aligned I'm working right now with my
PhD student on the constitution of
epistemic communities so like it sounds
very abstract in one sense but like so
think of like you know you seen these
maps of like the the us like electoral
politics and everything where you have
like these little islands of blue and
these seas of red right yeah so close
they are of the perspective that we're
advancing here I mean it may be that
like people are literally living in
different worlds in the sense that like
they are no longer the same kind of
creature they don't they don't have the
same generative model like just the we
we've effectively you know the the
course of politics and for example the
United States but I think increasingly
elsewhere especially I mean like the
information environments in which we're
living in I'm just so like because we
can select what we you know through
Twitter Facebook and how these social
media environments we can construct our
own information
and they in turn construct us and what I
think is yeah and that is a beautiful
point and that this is one of the things
that we've really drilled down on on the
active in the active inference family of
things
I mean you in the discussion before we
started you mentioned axial constant
who's a really close friend and
collaborator an axle is responsible for
also with the yellow Brandenburg but
Axel is like one of the people who's
really championed this for the idea that
well so the active Infernus formulation
is symmetric you know I was telling you
about the this predictability stuff
earlier that like you can predict stuff
about the environment given my
phenotypic state
well not symmetrical okay like you can
predict something about the kind of
things that live in an environment by
looking at the physical structure of the
environment like the relations of
prediction are kind of circular in that
way and certain creatures like ants and
beavers and humans have evolved such
that like we we extend our statistical
models into the world like we we we
ought meant the physical world with but
by allowing it to encode information
that we can use to guide our behavior so
think of like you know the fact that in
most big cities streets meet at right
angles isn't accidental right it's a
feature that we design right into the
physical layout of our cities to to
improve our predictive grip on them
essentially like to make it to make our
coping with them smoother same goes for
like you know traffic signals and stuff
like that so I mean there's a sense in
which this story opens on to something
like and this is what we're exploring in
in our current work like the this kind
of opens on to a story of epistemic
communities and like epistemic Miche
creation right like we we we design
environments
in order to better like to get a better
predictive grip on our environments and
that might explain in part like the kind
of fragmentation that you see right like
that we're literally creating two
different kinds of worlds that are
embodying two different kinds of well
outlooks or we would put it in terms of
different generative models yeah yeah
yeah a direction that I'm very excited
to pursue actually I think you know what
there's a lot to say there sure and when
you consider that so right I haven't
made a public yet but it's um it's a I
guess it's two articles one is just on
the Internet and control and why how
it's a human rights issue and one is
that the Internet is just necessary for
securing human rights and secondly we do
not like our access to like it is it is
so vital today but our access to it is
actually well it's under threat at all
times we may not know it but like it
could be taken away from us at any point
and in some places it has been I mean
China is the greatest example of
government censorship but there's like
dozens of countries have stopped social
media or like interfere with social
media and messaging apps and when the
state or went you know privately held
interests can effectively dictate what
is in one's information environment they
can do a whole range of things from
manufacturing consent to well you know
just changing how people think and and
and how they acts in the world and I
think it's a it's a huge huge problem
and one that like I don't really know
what the solution is because if you know
if you take the liberal idea that you
know we should be free to go out and do
is do whatever he wants within reason
within certain bounds but you know I
should be able to expose myself to
whatever information I feel like as long
as it's you know not hurting anyone or
anything if that's actually if we agree
with that then we can't actually impose
these informational constraint
saying that you know it's all well and
good for each for you to go ahead and do
that however we need you to be
we need our generative models to be
somewhat coherent or we will conflict yo
or things just break down yeah like in a
really deep way yeah I totally agree I
mean you know what a huge issue is uh
whose principle is it that it takes it
takes an order of magnitude more energy
to dispel than it does to
create it right
someone's rule I forget I forget what
whose rule it is but I mean yeah the
that's a real issue I think you know the
I mean I I I'm definitely not a liberal
I'm not a conservative either so I think
you can kind of situate me you know
pretty clearly uh yeah no I I don't I
I'm sort of grappling with the same kind
of issues that you are here like I yeah
I also value freedom of speech and
freedom of expression but on the flip
side like there is something like
there's like an ecology of memes you
know like the there there there's only
so much like physical space that ideas
can occupy right so like that I mean you
know minds are like in on the net oh
yeah on the net and like physically in
space yeah as well they're technically
the same right like ah yeah I mean that
is an embodiment yeah exactly
it isn't Bartek yeah so I mean I'm
sensitive to that I I'm very worried
about like the creation of like these
fact resistant you know bubbles
uh but you know like the there's a sense
in which like I think the the current
Information Age exposes a lot of our
kind of innate shipping inherited like
evolutionarily old psychology right you
know like the what gets called virtue
signaling oh yeah I think I think happen
is both on the left and on the right the
show official I think ultimately the
problem is that like we we have
forgotten how to engage with ideas and
what takes the place of engagement with
ideas is signaling to your in-group
whoever your in-group is your values are
consonant with theirs in my last
conversation we kind of touched on this
and one of the observations that the
guest Matthew Bukowski made which is you
know very very passionate and and true
is is that social media kind of it
rewards signaling but not action yeah
like we're all engaged you know we're
incentivized to just signal great things
right things about our lives or our
ideas or whatever and that signaling is
enough it doesn't really matter if we're
going out and doing stuff and we need to
move from signaling to action especially
in the filter to your Facebook I stand
for you know breast cancer victims like
oh you've just saved it
you've just your cell with it and you
know I think we're all guilty of this I
am myself absolutely and that's what I'm
saying like I think it's a it's an issue
everywhere it's it's an issue you hear
about it a lot because like right-wing
pundits accused like left-wing activists
of virtue signaling a lot but I mean III
think you can see the same essential
cognitive strategy redeployed everywhere
essentially so I mean that that's that's
something that's sort of unfortunately
predicted by the kind of theory that we
were working with oh that's brutal
yeah well because like what you're what
we're saying ultimately is the work
action is in the surface is in the
service of generating evidence for our
beliefs essentially
right so like things that things that
conform to our broader yeah so like it
it takes a lot more cognitive energy to
like confront you know observations and
data that don't provide evidence for
your belief and in actually her I mean
in literals yeah yeah and I think it's
like I think of this as like we are
constructed by of we are information
right like who we are these are the
ideas like the person I think I am is a
collection of these ideas and I've kind
of brought together and right I identify
with and if I find something that I
disagrees with them I am actually being
attacked in some in some way right and I
think that's where that pain comes from
because it's like there's some oh yeah I
made that is was a lot more complicated
because I mean you know left and right
what you're seeing today is a rise of
identity centered politics I don't want
to repeat like you know kind of dumb
right-wing tropes about identity
politics yeah yeah it is true but like a
lot of the politics that we see today on
the left and on the right concern
questions essentially relating to
identity right yep so you know it's not
virtual it's not first as we spoke about
earlier um like that you can basically
categorize something an infinite number
of ways some categories are just kind of
a bit better at like at whatever you're
trying to do so on the one hand I don't
want to compromise like I you know
activism based on legitimate you know
like you're suffering of a particular
group in house right yeah the show of a
showing it like you know denunciations
of you know forms of oppression that are
rooted and like I don't know in the u.s.
like you know slavery
yeah elsewhere like and you know
histories of colonialism and everything
I mean you know as an Australian in the
Canadian we should know a thing or two
about like colonialism right you know we
come from countries where like you know
it's some of the only like actually
quote-unquote successful genocides have
been carried out right
oceans of blood yeah exactly where
people have been systematically
exterminated like and where we're like
that was carried to completion I mean in
there are places in Canada where that
was carried out against four stations
people and I mean you know the this is
the actual genocide of the conquering
like all that and you know the same
thing with in Tasmania or the yeah so I
mean I don't want to minimize those
legitimate airings of you know like or
but but on the flip side like when when
you make your identity into your thesis
it becomes very dangerous to disagree or
to argue about that you know so like if
your main thing is all if your main
thesis is like us something about you
know American identity real American
patriot or whatever then it seems to me
that like you know disagreement will
quickly collapse into like yeah you're
attacking my identity yeah like my
deeply held sense of Who I am so I mean
III also think it's probably not the
most productive way to the frame
discussion on the flip side like I
haven't quite squared the circle of how
you how you recognize that danger on the
one hand and also recognize the
legitimacy of identity based you know
like legitimate grievances and being
there a yes it's a tough one I think one
way that kind of it doesn't solve it it
doesn't definitely doesn't solve the
problem but I think a lot of this
discussion of identity is rooted in
inequality problems of equality and I
think there's too much of a focus on
equality in terms of income and wealth
even though it's a great proxy for
well-being and all that it's just not
good enough the quality of opportunity
is something that we should really be
focusing on more and as I
said you know wealth is a great proxy
for that but if you can't read it
doesn't matter how much money you have
right um you don't have as acts you
don't have as much access to the world
as someone who is literate or if you
have shelter or if you're adequately
nourished you have access to the
Internet so by focusing on I really like
the idea of focusing on equality of
opportunity and seeing like the
importance of increasing the landscape
of opportunity to people because if you
think it like freedom is in binary right
freedom exists in degrees and if if we
want if one of the aims of society is to
ensure that our citizens are flourishing
one way of ensuring that that happens is
like you make them as free as possible
like an increased landscape of
opportunity as much as possible so they
can go and choose to do things it's in
to it in order to do that you need to
ensure that they have their basic needs
taken care of sir you know shelter
nutrition the ability to read perhaps
all these things increase the landscape
of freedom and then the individual they
know their map of themselves is the best
right there's nothing better than their
internal map of themselves so they will
choose to live a life that maximizes for
their own flourishing so if we wish to
ensure that our populations are
flourishing we sort of should kind of
increase the degrees of freedom that I
made available to them and let them
navigate an unfortunate thing about
neoliberalism is that you know in in in
the current kind of set up what freedom
means is like the freedom to choose
between 36 different flavors of ice
cream yeah yeah it's I think it's just a
bit of it I don't think when we had
these conversations wildly enough like
what is the purpose of society know what
is government working towards like what
does a good life mean I mean I think you
know we might have that conversation
around a campfire with a joint you know
but it's like so we don't hear like our
politicians actually having these
conversations all I hear is this retro
jobs yeah I totally agree I mean so I've
been setting up a an international
Neuroscience network over the last year
or so and we're really trying to
foreground ethical reflection because
currently I mean you know this whole
ethics review board business is
basically a box ticking exercise
right we're like you know in science the
way that it basically works as well you
know when when they were like figuring
out like these you know the wording of
these Accords right like the regulate
research on humans then they involved
philosophers and everything but like
it's sort of like they settled
everything you know wet like at that
point and from now we're not really
thinking about like the ethical
implications of our research we're just
making sure that no one's gonna sue us
yeah which is what the IRB is do so
we've effectively evacuated ethical
discussion from like the practice of
science and so yeah ethics usually means
in science like you got a board to
review and it's pretty safe from a legal
point of view like there's not gonna be
any like legal blowback yeah well that's
a very very thin conception of like
ethical reflection about the scientific
process I mean I couldn't agree more
with you like the these things have
really been sidelined like much to
everyone's detriment I think yeah yeah
it's I think we're gonna see a
resurgence in well ethics ethical
discussions ethical thinking I mean we
were I think that we already have it's
just like done through the guise of
environmentalism and you know like
fighting for the biosphere and you know
humanitarianism so I take that back
ethics is still there we just don't talk
about as ethics for like we just appeal
to you know human nature but I'm really
excited to and this is one of the
reasons we're I'm spoke to you what I'm
where I wanted to speak to you and I
think will guide a lot of the
conversations that I'll have over the
next future over the coming the coming
weeks and months and years but it's just
like what are the physical
characteristics of things that are like
what is the material basis for that
which is good you know
like if you if you take damn I mean you
know well there's a question like yeah
well I think like it's I think we have
like some of a somewhat of an idea like
just intuitively like systems that are
complex like there seems to be
a correlation between the complexity of
the system however you wish to measure
it and its ethical value right so I'm
excellent I have an ongoing disagreement
about this the the disagreement is
basically axel thinks that morality
itself can be absorbed under the free
energy principle and I don't necessarily
disagree but I want to push back against
that as much as I can so for the simple
the following reason like I think that
like you know with the free energy
principle etc will will tell you is
where the system is converging how it's
converging like what it is converging
towards essentially right like so - no
that doesn't mean that it's a good idea
that things are converging in that
direction though yeah see that's like
this objective like there is this
objective morality that states that that
thing that is that you were converging
towards is good right it's like separate
but I see morality is like it's actually
emergent as well right
like you let me and maybe perspectival
so if let's take this account seriously
it sort of implies that morality is
embodied in a shared generative model
right that like has effects in terms of
like you know allowable cultural
practices allowable ways of like living
in the shared environment but the
implication of that is that like you
know the kind of moral standards are
ultimately relative to you know the
shared generative model so that like
what do you do then when there are
groups of people who come into contact
that don't share a generative model like
I like I I find it difficult to because
the scientist in need doesn't see like
the the possibility of there being like
some sort of external way to arbitrate
between the sets of so it's irreducibly
complex right and but we cannot put like
it's it's too chaotic we can't predict
any of this it's something we can just
plug things into a formula and then say
oh look this is the more ethical
decision it's just like exactly
impossible precisely I mean I
you can only find the most likely
decision no I think I think that's where
these heuristics come in right like you
know thou shalt not kill like these 10
commandments are like they're kind of
just like guide rails for Humanity
because a lot of it's really hard like
we I think we've been trying to like
figure out what we're like what is good
and I think you know like these like the
the the rule based stuff is just kind of
like oh we've got a bit of an idea like
9 times out of 10 these rules are right
the question of like I think there is
like some material I think this can be
described in terms of energy and
information I'm just not too sure how
but I think it's like if you were to
take a word that's that's what Axl ends
up saying I think I don't want to put
words into his mouth but yeah the ends
up saying something like well you know
it is about constructing the right
generative model so if if we can if we
can just like get a picture of what the
adequate moral system would look like
and all share this generative model then
you know we would end up converging to
something like you know a socially
acceptable situation so I guess this
brings me to write the last topic I want
to count before we wrap up and we're
kind of speaking about it before but one
of the implications so like I guess
logical evolutions of this just applying
of the free energy principle applying it
to humanity is just like they need for
like we are a social species we are
engaging at scales that are you know
increasing as as the years progress if
we are trying to minimize surprise for
you know to put it put it in those terms
and one things one of the things that we
really really need to do is integrate
the sciences into our politics into our
decision-making because like it is it is
truly a matter of survival and we may be
hit with some things that I mean they
may not be too surprising to some but
you know coded
the array of challenges that we're
facing with which actually threaten our
not only our survival but like the
survival of you know lots of life on on
the planet like it makes what the free
energy principle says to me is that we
actually need to take these epistemic
tools like you know science like these
frameworks these ways of being in the
world and extracting information and
putting it to use and actually making
them a part of our as our culture in a
way that's far more like far more
embedded and far more well I guess
useful is sort of an ethical imperative
the falls out of it I think with the
free energy principle would tell you is
that well if you don't do this you're no
longer gonna exist at non-equilibrium
steady-state right it's just that but
that is where we're going collapse
that's where we're going so yeah I mean
the the the issue is it again has to do
with generative moles it's like the
generative models typically have a
temporal depth built into them so
basically like how many times steps into
the future is your model able to model
effectively and I mean it may just be
that like the the temporal scales at
which were actually having an effect on
the planet don't match up to the
temporal depth of the models that we're
using to deal with so like you know the
the the time of everyday phenomenology
is kind of a cyclical kind of like
24-hour thing where like you'll plan
maybe a few weeks or months or maybe
years ahead but like there's a mismatch
between that scale right like the scale
of the generative models that we use
effectively in everyday behavior and the
scale of the effects that we're having
on the environment so I think that the
the you know the political decisions
political decisions are made with like a
two-year window at most right maybe four
depending on the country but like you
know it's little guarantee the next
election you know it so of course
there's like this huge incommensurate
ility right like because the the the
timescales of our practical can
and the time scales at which the threats
the existential threats to you know our
continued existence as a species like
that it's this in commence or ability
that I think needs to be bridged yeah
with any hope of you know yeah that's um
that's a natural article that's where
I'm cynical I think if anything like
this rise of virtue signaling you know
on the left and on the right it points
to the fact that like you know the the
the kind of disembodied ideal of a
rational actor you know it isn't really
what's at play here like people are I
mean I think at was Isaac Asimov who
said you know our fundamental
predicament is that we have Paleolithic
Minds medieval social institutions and
godlike technology right like with our
minds like our brains were optimized to
handle you know it's Dunbar's number
right it's an each of about 150 people
timescales you know the point of culture
in part the conservative power of
culture is to obviate the need to think
about long term regularities in any kind
of detail I mean that's the point of
constructing a niche you don't have to
deal with time because everything that
you need to deal with the temporality of
the world is already pre encoded in our
practices and in the physical layout of
an environment
so like the I see no reason to believe
that like suddenly we're gonna start
shifting our perspective if anything I
think like you know we we've constructed
like these these informational Ecology's
that make us more resistant to actually
you know challenging the depth like the
temporal horizon at which we're engaging
with phenomena and rather just like
signal to our you know our people like
us that we're on we're on the right side
of history we're doing this right and
they disagree because they're bad guys I
think that's far more likely that you
know
I maybe maybe the promise of these meta
Bayesian approaches that I was alluding
to you miss to kind of sketch you know
some paths or ins yeah actually like
doing that without an you know
infringing upon people's freedoms like
if you just look at the US like they
have as freedom-loving and I use that I
say egg quotes because like I think
they've got a certain view of freedom
that I don't think everyone would agree
with you know like you are free if you
have a gun you know you are more free if
you have you know you can bear arms or
if you don't have your text as you'd
have to pay as much in taxes because you
know taxes of theft and I think I'll um
be right yeah I just hope that like I
think one of the most important things
is as we said like taking our so we have
evolved to exist in smaller tribes right
but one of the wonderful things is we
have developed this capacity to extract
really useful information from the world
and explain phenomena with it right back
science and our challenge is to like
take this you know godlike capability
and use it with look I mean look just
just to be a bit like self-critical so
I'm not a climate scientist right I
think I don't I don't annoy just a stop
right so like when I when I say I
believe like human climate change is
real that's an act of faith on my part
yeah right and so like yeah my suspicion
is that that encapsulate like the human
thought process like ultimately like
there's something about like deferring
to whatever is the default belief of the
community that I feel that I belong to
you that's like the main mode of
operation even when we think that it
yields results that we find are good
right so you know I'm also part of this
more like progressive anti-racist
you know feminist
and agenda but you know you might say
that's I'm like this because those are
the ideas that are available in my eco
Miche I'm just you know conforming to
whatever is so I think the the person
who articulates this most beautifully is
Joseph Henrich I really I really like I
really really like Joe he's great he's
uh he's based at Harvard
he's like a an evolutionary biologist
anthropologist and he works on the self
domestication of humans and so he says
well basically the the those very
mechanisms that enable us to perform
like these large-scale feats of
incredible coordination right the things
that make us like agreeable
and able to cooperate with one another
are also the things that like you know
make us susceptible to fascism and to
like authoritarian dictatorships were
agreeable we just go with things you
know like they're not the typical Nazi
wasn't like a raging racist yeah
you know they were just like
quote-unquote good people just trying
not to rock the boat and just going with
whatever the and so you know that's
really what like I think it's too easy
for us to say like oh well clearly you
know like we're on the right side of
this because our beliefs happen to line
up with whatever is the case in reality
the cognitive operations that I go
through to say like well you know I
believe in man-made human-made climate
change are essentially the same is like
an empty box are going like oh well you
know like I like I can't myself verify
that this is the case mmm I don't know
the science like ah my my my opinion
rests on this division of labor but the
yeah so I'm not particularly optimistic
yeah look I've never thought about it in
that way and you've just made me a
little bit more pessimistic like I've
never really thought about like that and
we are like I just his face faith-based
yeah yeah yeah because I have looked at
them
I like riotous assume the experts are
experts in ER and just less trusted but
everyone assumes that they're experts or
experts right yeah that's the thing
that's that's what's sharing a
generative model is about but at the
same time like there's like that's
that's all that's true but then when you
think about climate change when you
think about that we are on this bounded
planet like you know it's a closed
system in many ways and that we are
there's like eight billion of us a lot
of us are using I think the value the
number is like 30 times our basal
metabolic rates you're like for us to
live the lives that we live we need 30
times amount of energy our bodies needs
like what do you think about that it
kind of makes sense that things might be
heating up you know like you don't need
to like really but I'm not denying
climate change no I I know you know I'm
like I don't think you need to be like
on this progressive side of things to
actually just go through that line of
reasoning do I critical ultimately the
the big filter is natural selection
right so we can have the beliefs that we
want and we can have the generative
models that we want but like if we're
too off we're gonna die
yeah and that's that's the bottleneck at
the end of the day and that's also why
I'm not super like optimistic because
like the the way that these shifts
happen typically is massive die-off yeah
I mean like that's how generative models
are not evolved a right the same way
that everything else ends up involving
like you know whether its cultural
selection or natural selection like you
know the maladaptive beliefs end up like
causing negative consequences to their
hammers and then not spread into the
future and so like yeah I agree
like you know I I think I personally I
think I have good reason to believe in
that make climate change and I also
think I have good reason to think that
if we don't take it seriously as a
factual matter of affairs and there will
be negative consequences but my fear is
just that like even if I know this my
motive justification is not
fundamentally different and the one
employed by people who believe in
chemtrails and you know where I gave fog
stuff like you know you heard Alex
if you didn't watch that podcast with
him Jurgen and no not the whole Robert I
mean it's ridiculous it's ridiculous to
fundamentally though like the difference
is that I have I have more epistemic
tools up my sleeve right I'm a scientist
able I don't know I don't have the exact
analytic tools that are used in climate
science but I do I do know like a
story out of anecdotes from you
know rigorous they have kind of reviews
of evidence but like fundamentally
though like it's it's sort of about it's
all about like the the kind of the so
Joe Henrik calls them creds credibility
enhancing displays you know it's it is
that there's an economy of authority you
know humans are the the only mammal
species with a prestige system that's
evolved independently of the dominant
system right so like what was that
system I just cut out a vestige okay
prestige so Preston he's just a kind of
freely conferred power right whereas
like dominance is you know you listen to
me because I'm gonna smack you if you
don't write like prestige is the kind of
thing that like you know Joe says the
the the the top top climber at the base
camp of the Himalaya right like everyone
wants to climb with this person yeah
because it just so happens she's the
best right she knows how to you know go
up the mountain she knows the path she
knows what did you like the he's
socially but it's it's like it's not
that she's conferred yeah right but
there's an economy of these of authority
like in in almost every society there's
a series of ritualized cues that
indicate who is the knowing cast right
so like you know scientists we're you
know sorrows and doctors have their
stethoscopes and teachers profs I mean
less and less maybe like in the North
American context but like you know profs
will often dress up you know people in
positions of power indicate not just
power but like people in positions of
epistemic Authority reliably indicate
with like Ecology's of cues that they
have this Authority means are just very
sensitive to these cues you know we so
it's it's you know it's it's what the
Milgram experiments for example so I
mean it's people deferred I mean I don't
know if Milgram still works anymore
wasn't good I think it's a bit dodgy it
was yeah but anyway like there are these
experiments from social psychology that
tend to show that people just defer to
whatever they think is a source of
authority and I think that's more
germane to human cognition than
strenuous putting into question of
whether the psychology of queues
actually reflects something so I just
think it's moral luck at the end of the
day if you and I are on the right side
of this kind of factual matter it's it's
not it's not because the vinegar true
that we cultivated we just happen to be
in the right at the semuc meteor that
allows us to make the right kind of
inferences yeah but so my my fear though
is that like making these kind of
fact-based inferences takes a lot of
energy and there are there are much
fewer people who are able to make them
than people who are like able to you
know subscribe on YouTube and start a
channel about chemtrails and whatever so
like I mean on the whole I'm not I I
don't know what's gonna happen I mean
III don't see any reason to be
optimistic
to be blunt oh well we can do our best
and see what happens I mean having said
that like I I think that the kinds of
tools that we're developing are giving
us a better
grip so for example like you know this
this generate shared generative model
business allows us to understand the
Constitution right and the maintenance
of epistemic communities in a robust way
that might be amenable we hope to
modeling into like experiment and so you
know it it may be that like by studying
the ways in which humans reason right
and reason on the basis of like
credibility enhancing displays right an
arbitrary between different sources of
epistemic Authority and so on it may be
that like you know through that process
mmm
you know none of its age dependent just
because I don't think we have much time
it may be so yeah I someone that I
really admire in the literature
she's a theoretical neuroscientist and
neuro imager she's with the neuro
imaging department at King's College and
she has this great model of how
basically the the parameter range of
your generative model becomes more and
more rigid as you grow older and that's
that's not because your brain is like
efficient it's that it's adaptive I mean
presumably when you're middle-aged
you should assuming like a relatively
stable structure in the environment you
should have less to learn than someone
who's like half your age you know that
there is a rigidify of the generative
models that's age dependent I mean my
own my own fear has to do with like the
the rapid generational shift so like you
know the boomers that gets so mulling
maligned in the you know just in the
media you know just abused and
everything will be they grew up in
another world yeah we're like you know
journalism was you know like everyone
had the same everyone had the same
informational environment right liking
right you just wasn't precisely because
there were like three sources of
information right so yeah so whereas
people I don't know exactly how you are
under 30
and so like I I grew up with the
internet and with the assumption
actually like part of what it is to have
a valid epistemic process is to bet you
know the source of the information where
you're getting this whereas like if you
grew up in that it's all to it it was
like you look at something and it's like
this is oh yeah but exactly but
if you grew up in an ecology where there
are three sources and information you
know like the the news at five you know
your local journal and whatever your
big-city journal is like then then your
relation to sources of information and
the very process by which you bet your
own beliefs is going to be radically
different yeah so it may be what we're
seeing now maybe like I mean you know
and I don't want to make it only into a
generational thing I mean there are a
young conspiracy theorists but it has to
do with like you know exploiting the
basic kind of you know mechanisms for
attributing epistemic Authority I mean
you know you'll notice like Trump does
this all the time you know like he
prefaced is his sentences with material
that would enhance his credibility in
certain communities right so saying like
you know I'm the best at Nenana no one
understands X better than I do like the
these these cues work in a community
were typically the people who say this
are the people who know right now so if
you grew up and you were uncultured in a
community where you know people who
signal in this way typically are right
about things and it's not surprising
that you'll end up like you know
adhering for this and I don't only want
to make it into a right-wing thing I
mean I think oh it's on the both sides
for sure for sure it's it's just we live
in such interesting times you know
Michael I think we're just see right now
is self-righteousness self-righteousness
yeah on everyone's side I think yeah
it's just you know from a philosophical
point of view I come from this tradition
called hermeneutics so I mean my
favorite philosopher is uh
this-this-this philosopher called
gadamer yeah gadamer's philosophy is a
philosophy of interpretation so
hermeneutics is sort of a corrective to
phenomenology phenomenology says let's
start from the first person lived
experience and its immediacy
hermeneutics says there's no such thing
as immediate first-person experience all
experience is all always already
mediated by structures of interpretation
but anyway I don't want to dwell on that
but I say this because gadamer says
beautifully somewhere like the starting
point of my philosophy is that my
interlocutor could be correct right like
I might be wrong
it's about interpretation and finding a
common interpretation and I think that's
been completely evacuated like the
discussion is about showing the other
person why they are wrong and showing
people on our side why we are so
virtuous right like the you know we're
really going to stick it to the lids or
you know just like finger-pointing and
calling people or whatever isn't as hot
today like it's like it's it's only it's
only epistemic this talk that we're
having this discussion is only epistemic
for show it's not really about epistemic
it's about confirming what I believe
right and so so telling you who disagree
with me that you have to be wrong
ultimately right and yeah it's it's it's
and about showing you know others that
you know we're we're also valid
epistemic agents you know I guess like
if that makes me think and you have to
thank you for a while and you know I'm
just echoing what I've heard a lot of
other people say but humility from you
know a scientific standpoint from the
standpoint of policy but also in our own
interactions with each other is has
never been more important right like
that we can learn from the person that
we're talking with or arguing with yeah
so that our actions like we actually
don't know what may happen in the world
we don't know how bad the current of
Irish could be we don't know whether or
not our climate change models are
actually correct and Ravin that we do
not know we need to be carried to be
extra careful because things could go
better than we think but things could
also go a lot worse yeah
precisely and you know we have to be
open to and again I'm not saying that we
have to listen to these crazy denialists
who you know cherry-pick their data and
who are obviously not like engaging in
the same kind of scientific process that
we are but like I especially mean like
moral certainties you know I mean it may
be that the way that we see the world
even even our our you know most deeply
cherished values maybe they're off you
know to a certain extent and and I think
that it's the it's the
self-righteousness of everyone involved
in these political conversations that
makes it and you know I'm a many minds
about this because on the same time you
know at the same time if someone's
position is that like we should
exterminate whatever you know a group of
people because of whatever you know
reason and that also doesn't
float you know like I I don't think that
we so it's it's it's all sorts of
complicated and I don't have any other
dancers I just look at the problem
honestly yeah well that's the first step
to solving it right mmm yeah
understanding it I mean the one thing we
didn't discuss is is what the approach
can't do so yeah there's good reason to
think that nature you know life if life
exists right if life is a useful concept
if we don't eliminate it from our
ontology there's a good reason to think
that life isn't a non-equilibrium steady
state process it isn't it isn't like the
so like evolution isn't going anywhere
right if life is this open-ended kind of
thing that's like a tree yeah exactly
yeah and and and it works on a process
of drift which is not predictable you
know like so
I mean natural selection works there is
variation selection retention right so
like that process is not so the the
technical term is ergodic so basically
everybody mean yeah average yeah yeah
yeah okay so like the so you know like
so if you think of the space of all
possible states of the system like an
ergodic system means that there's some
density towards which the system
eventually converges right such that on
average so that the average of your
measures will converge to a measure of
your average yeah because there is a
density at the end of the day right okay
there's reason to think and in fact like
I'm working with people who are showing
this experimental II there's reason to
think that at several relevant scales
there is a non-equilibrium steady state
density one of the easy demonstrations
of this is that you I assume I mean
maybe you have a different physiology
for climbing but like you're roughly the
same height from day to day right your
your your blood pressure is roughly in
the same or in the same neighborhood you
know you're all that you have these
these states that you revisit frequently
you know the such that you can say that
there's something like ass phenotype all
right that you returned to
characteristically but evolution itself
is an open-ended process that might not
have such a like an endpoint right so so
like right now the the formulation is in
terms of non-equilibrium steady state
systems but it doesn't extend to non
equilibrium non steady state systems so
so the ways right given the time scale
we're not non steady it's really like it
depends on your temporal scale in scale
at which this doesn't apply yeah yeah
yeah and in fact like it may be that
like the the more socially interesting
stuff that you're interested in can't
interests by this framework for
precisely that reason what basically if
if the attractor doesn't exist yet
there's nothing you can do from
variational e like there's nothing to
converge to mmm well sort of right I
agree there's no there's no point of
convergence however one tenant that you
could say is the need to survive right
and a part of that diversity of
approaches so well so you can still get
something out of it so you can say like
there are like you can say there are
something like different attractors that
are competing right so there's the
liberal the progressive and the
conservative kind of attractors those
sort of competing for where the overall
trajectory but you might say that but
look like what I want to say is
something like well you can use the
current formulation to model something
like feudal friends but not France
during like the Revolution and the
terror when they're there just isn't a
clear attractor like so the entire
approach rests on being able to write
down this non-equilibrium steady-state
density like this the phenotype if
you're able to characterize the
phenotype then you gave us this effect
so that's their problem right like life
is a process it's not discrete it's like
so you're constantly becoming I mean and
I I didn't the way I think about life
and death more specifically is that we
don't really die like we like life is
just about information creation
consolidation and propagation and we are
just apart we're just passing the baton
right like we live on through our
genetic code but also through the
culture the ideas possessing I couldn't
agree more
yeah yeah all I'm saying is that like
you know and and as an advocate of the
approach work I also want to hope that
there's a way to extend the the
formalism to non steady state systems
but if you're asking me like what can't
this do because it does seem like it can
do almost everything
well so what Kant did do the historical
change mmm can't do it right now like
III for principled reasons this isn't
like
an accident but like so you know the
approach hasn't yet been applied to the
formation of epistemic communities
that's not a principled limitation it's
just that it hasn't been done yet
yeah so that's what we're doing well if
this is hammer and there's so many nails
now right exactly but like this may be a
principle limitation it may be that this
kind of approach can is only conceivable
for non-equilibrium steady-state system
and certainly the current mathematical
formulation even in Carl's like totally
integrative 20/20 like monograph that
really contains like the whole approach
even there like it's formulated in terms
of non equilibrium steady state so it
may be that like and this is what's
frustrating for me as a scientist like
maybe the most important questions are
not can't be addressed in this kind of
framework because at least the most
ethically important questions may be
those have to do with when the attractor
hasn't consolidated maybe I don't know
or if there even is one right like it
like that's I think I've on the promise
of like ethics in general it's like well
is there an objective good and like what
are we moving towards and like I think
in a way it's kind of the wrong question
I don't think there is an objective good
like if you take it fueling materials
the materialist approach like we have
just like minimizing entropy locally and
trying to do the best as possible as we
move up scales and when I say we I mean
life in general right and that morality
is emergent and like I think like
obviously we'd say that like that which
is more complex so that you know like
life is good like if you think of the
world with life or no life we'd say that
life is good we're obviously biased but
I don't think there's anything wrong
with like to say there's this that
there's no like if you take this
perspective that we have just kind of
emerged from soup and morality has come
with it and that there may I believe
that there would be things that are that
all forms of life intelligent life would
think would deemed to be of moral worth
so you can think of that as objectively
moral but like to see there as being
objective morality extricated from life
I just I don't think that makes any
sense you know I I agree and that's
consonant with the framework that we're
too
since from from our vantage point
morality is just encoded in a specific
kind of shared generative model you know
so so my question so let's say there's
two worlds right and I know that I have
to choose between one and I've got a
flourishing ecosystem bamas only
rainforest or I've got a shitty one like
a desert right I just say one of them
has to exist which one would exist
everyone would choose the Amazon
rainforest one not everyone if you're a
Bedouin you'll prefer the desert
yeah but I think like they are I think
on average and I think that is important
right because it depends on what you've
like you're adapted to like I think that
we are like we have moral intuitions
that point us in the direction of that
which promotes order and survival and
the increasing and here's the rub like
that is defined in terms of the
non-equilibrium steady-state density so
you're still not out of the woods it's
not objective like the the good is just
defined in terms of like and like our
body's adapted this so I'm a Canadian
like you know when it's five degrees
Celsius outside I can go outside in a
t-shirt and I'm totally fine like but I
don't handle the heat well like when I
went to Australia Jesus Christ like I
went in February and Sydney just kicked
my ass
like I just can't handle this 40 degree
heat so I lived in Malaysia right and
I'm like you I can I can handle a cult
but the heat just ruins me so I had a
sweating problem and I just realized I
was just in their own country well but
your body does adapt I mean like after
several months of this you start
sweating less and that's what I mean
though is like the third you know it's
all about the complete package of priors
that you embody so there really isn't
the way to say well this is good and
this is bad I mean you know think of
like a preference for spicy foods I mean
it's even or sad Oh masochism as a sex
thing I mean it's it's just
it's just the case that like you know
there's no objective kind of mapping
it's just whatever is you know like
whatever is available and whatever can
lead to like a targeted configuration I
mean the the bit that I kind of skipped
over for the social stuff is that like
what's sharing a generative model allows
you to do at the end since you're
sharing all your expectations is to
arrive at the same target configuration
so all of these multi scale models they
rest on the idea that a bunch of
components sharing a generative model if
they engage in individual inference they
can still reach this kind of target
configuration so that's how all of this
morphogenesis cellular differentiation
stuff inactive in family and when I met
Carl what made my nose bleed initially
was him telling me you know the exact
same mathematics that we use in the
morphogenesis stuff you could use in the
social stuff because it's it's it's
sharing a generative model it's just
that in one case the generative model is
a metaphor for a shared genetic and
epigenetic code like when what you're
modeling is like cellular
differentiation the genetic code is a
shared generative model that tells every
cell well what kind of thing should you
expect sentence given the kind of cell
that you are right so the the same the
very same mathematical framework applies
to social dynamics it's just that rather
than you know what kind of you know
intracellular signalling you're
expecting it's what kind of social cues
do I expect to see right but it's the
same idea yeah yeah why is it a target
configuration by sharing a generative
mall and the twist for the whole
multiscale story is that like the this
can be reiterated infinitely so your
cells share expectations that cell
networks share expectations organ
networks you know organisms
yeah mall or social groups like the
family unit larger social groups like a
like a community like all of these can
be cast as like successive recursively
nested
of a system that at each level share the
same generative model and they're all
doing the same thing example is a cell
that doesn't write it was like a cancer
cell doesn't have the same generative
model as your other cells because it's
genetic material has been altered you
know so that's really the perspective
from which I'm coming to understand like
it's also why I'm so pessimistic to be
honest with you I mean the thing that
you see is that you need to share a
generative model to for there to be a
target configuration right like the the
the share generative model is what
induces the non-equilibrium steady state
at the superordinate level the fact that
we all share the same generative model
means that our our behavior will look as
if it's converging toward some kind of
phenotype at the high dose that's how
you get cool like self-organization that
scales like that exactly okay
that's what dropping me drew me into the
free energy principle initially so we
need that I just static global like I
had a planetary and I own now yeah but
then the question is can we construct
the generative model that's both complex
enough to like capture this kind of you
know that the model is complex enough to
capture the complexity of the phenomenon
but also transmissible you know like one
of the big problems that we're having
right now in the approach is that like
this all rests on like this high-flying
one of the things that people don't get
about this is that I get builds on
quantum mechanics it builds on classical
mechanics it builds on thermodynamics so
it's much more complicated than quantum
mechanics so like you know there's
there's a transmission issue that gets
in the way at some point because like
not everyone can be expected to like
assimilate that level look like that's
why I wanted to have this conversation
because like I'm I can like read stuff
and understand it like generally like
looks like I'm the genius but I
sometimes I can read stuff and sort of
get picture
but this stuff is a bit impenetrable
like I don't have a mathematics
mathematical background and yeah I mean
unfortunately like the math is required
yeah it's not like it's not like a gloss
it's that like it's sort of like look if
I ask you you know bees make honey combs
right yeah why are honey combs shaped
the way they are as strength and
space-filling yes precisely it's
space-filling it's that hexagons are
like one of the one of the geometrically
optimal ways to tessellate or to
completely cover a two-dimensional space
so in this case it's a bit of math that
explains the behavior is that like you
need to appeal to the mathematical fact
that heggs hexagons can completely
tessellate a 2d surface and this can be
generalized into three dimensions right
like you need that piece of math to
explain the behavior of these so what
asks where I need to know right here I
mean the only way to do that is to like
really slowly go through the literature
I mean I've been doing this like I've
just been doing active in different
stuff basically since 2014 and I'm still
learning but I mean like you know the
really it's a multidisciplinary approach
like there are people from computer
science there are people from physics
there are people from philosophy and at
from anthropology and like the full
picture is bigger than any any one
person with their tools set can address
well max well I think I've taken a
decent chunk of your time today
sir they carry in your f oh yeah yeah
it's been lots of fun um if people want
to find out about your work keep up to
date with it where should they go online
how can they find you online
well I mean I'm on research gay and
academia.edu but all of my research
basically yeah essentially everything
I've ever written is available either as
a preprint or open access actually the
vast majority
my publications are available up in
access so I like to say that my hockey
card is my Google Scholar account yeah
yeah really I like that I like a Twitter
account if you want i i'm also on
twitter i Twitter's my public kind of
academic thing so like I keep I keep
everyone up to date like when this is
released all OH I'll advertise it on my
Twitter so yeah Twitter is the best way
to keep like in the loop but like all of
my work is accessible on my Google
Scholar account like you'll find links
to all of the manuscripts for free so
has been wonderful okay that's been good
cuz I mean is research for this right
it's nice actually yes I mean you know
we we we we are definitely not in favor
of paywalls and stuff so yeah all of my
stuff is accessible so yeah yeah thank
you for thank you for the invitation
honestly Sam this has been very very
enjoyable yeah that's a good fun it's
been good fun thanks for taking the time
and uh yeah I'm sure we'll do it again
sometime soon yeah I'd love to and
whenever you want me back it was really
a pleasure so oh so uh yeah let's do it
again